<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>What's on Johan's mind</title>
  <link href="https://johan.im/mind.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://johan.im/mind"/>
  <id>https://johan.im/mind</id>
  
  <updated>2022-10-27T20:24:17Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Johan Brook</name>
    <email>webmaster@johan.im</email>
  </author>
  
  <entry>
    <title>October 27th, 2022 at 8:24:17 PM GMT+0</title>
    <link href="https://johan.im/mind#202210272024" />
    <updated>2022-10-27T20:24:17Z</updated>
    <id>https://johan.im/mind#202210272024</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;hi again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;last week, i was in portugal 🇵🇹 (right on the coast) with the rest of lookback. it was lovely to see everybody again. the heart is truly filled until next time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;we&#39;re going to south africa 🇿🇦 in november! we&#39;re gonna be in franschhoek and kalk bay, on the cape. really looking forward, since a) i&#39;ve never been in south africa, b) after researching, everything seem so cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;for the month long trip, i&#39;ve made a list of books to read:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Spy Who Came In From The Cold&lt;/em&gt;, by John le Carré&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Grand Union&lt;/em&gt;, by Zadie Smith&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vargarna Från Evighetens Skog&lt;/em&gt;, by Karl Ove Knausgård&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;At the Existentialist Café: Freedom, Being, and Apricot Cocktails&lt;/em&gt;, by Sarah Bakewell&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;What We Owe the Future&lt;/em&gt;, by William MacAskill.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;just the action of making this list makes me excited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;red hot chili peppers&#39; latest album &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/album/0KJc9ksnoJJsdpQxV3z5i1?si=n5gq6c42Tpm54YKkAY9DlA&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;return to the dream canteen&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt; is so good. i love anthony&#39;s smooth vocals, and john&#39;s solid guitar. they&#39;re so very musical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;i&#39;ve bought an watch even though i&#39;ve said i wouldn&#39;t. to my defense, it was a) a used one, and b) i&#39;ll only use it for exercising. it&#39;s really nice to not bring the phone when running, since i wanna track how good i do. however, i&#39;m really impressed by the watch so far. it&#39;s really a marvel of engineering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;i watch &amp;quot;house of the dragon&amp;quot; on HBO, and &amp;quot;rings of power&amp;quot; on amazon prime. the former is really good: even though it doesn&#39;t have the intricate storylines from &amp;quot;game of thrones&amp;quot;, i like the acting and focus on relationships between parents and children. i also appreciate the focus on the hardships for women of giving birth. &amp;quot;rings of power&amp;quot; is so-so. it feels too CGI, i think, and too &amp;quot;joyful&amp;quot;. it doesn&#39;t have the raw feeling of peter jackson&#39;s trilogy.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>August 28th, 2022 at 7:15:48 PM GMT+0</title>
    <link href="https://johan.im/mind#202208281915" />
    <updated>2022-08-28T19:15:48Z</updated>
    <id>https://johan.im/mind#202208281915</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;i bought myself a &lt;a href=&quot;https://global.hario.com/pickup03.html&quot;&gt;Hario Filter-in Bottle&lt;/a&gt; for making cold brew tea from a recommendation from a friend. excited for my new life as health guru.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>July 16th, 2022 at 6:54:33 PM GMT+0</title>
    <link href="https://johan.im/mind#202207161854" />
    <updated>2022-07-16T18:54:33Z</updated>
    <id>https://johan.im/mind#202207161854</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;lookie here, haven&#39;t posted in a while. this is how it goes when you have a full time job, and not being on parental leave!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;for my own memory, these are things i want to check out at the moment:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.solidjs.com/&quot;&gt;SolidJS framework&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;building a UI frontend for managing static site generators with &lt;a href=&quot;https://tauri.app/&quot;&gt;tauri&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;my work-in-progress app for reminding me to get in touch with friends, using &lt;a href=&quot;https://remix.run/&quot;&gt;remix&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;overall, things are pretty chill. i&#39;m &lt;a href=&quot;https://johan.im/reading&quot;&gt;reading&lt;/a&gt; the autobiography of keith richards, and i&#39;m actually enjoying it. thought it would be another sleazy rock star bio, but it kind &amp;quot;sounds&amp;quot; like he actually wrote it. also, he&#39;s got a great memory. too bad i want to buy a new acoustic guitar now, AND an electric one… 💸&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;i&#39;m enjoying watching the women&#39;s euro cup in football. there are so much less free kicks overall, due to … they&#39;re doing less movie tricks i guess? or are just toucher. the quality is super high (more than a few years ago, they say), and i appreciate it a lot.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>May 3rd, 2022 at 7:37:08 PM GMT+0</title>
    <link href="https://johan.im/mind#202205031937" />
    <updated>2022-05-03T19:37:08Z</updated>
    <id>https://johan.im/mind#202205031937</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;the musical experience which had most impact on me was one time in gothenburg, at a sleazy karaoke
bar. one woman came up to the mic, and it &lt;em&gt;looked&lt;/em&gt; like she had been through a lot in her life. i
don&#39;t know, i just felt it. then she went on and did the most emotional and beautiful version of
alanis morissette&#39;s &amp;quot;ironic&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;totally blew me away. the song was &lt;em&gt;hers&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>April 6th, 2022 at 6:07:55 PM GMT+0</title>
    <link href="https://johan.im/mind#202204061807" />
    <updated>2022-04-06T18:07:55Z</updated>
    <id>https://johan.im/mind#202204061807</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;finished two shows today: Euphoria S02 and Pam &amp;amp; Tommy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Euphoria is simply amazing. i loved season one. season two is grittier, and while it uses violence,
sex, and drugs to describe the world, it’s always the characters that shine through. i’ve never seen
better acting than zendaya’s performance as rue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;pam &amp;amp; tommy is kinda of a curve ball. i like it! i didn’t think i would. it manages to take a story
(pamela anderson &amp;amp; tommy lee’s stolen sex tape in the 90s) and make a whole series about it. i liked
the sentimental rendition of their mutual love for each other. also, the issue of men vs. women in
terms of leaked nudes is also brought up. “i was in that tape too!”, says tommy. “it’s not the same!
i’m.. i’m.. a woman!”, says pamela. and it’s not just hollow talk: the series actually manages to
showcase how pamela suffered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;i also appreciated the 90s LA vibe ☀️&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>March 16th, 2022 at 7:58:41 PM GMT+0</title>
    <link href="https://johan.im/mind#202203161958" />
    <updated>2022-03-16T19:58:41Z</updated>
    <id>https://johan.im/mind#202203161958</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;i don&#39;t think everyone need heavy test runners and framework for every project. a single file with
&lt;code&gt;import assert from &#39;assert&#39;&lt;/code&gt; (node) and a bunch of assertions can suffice for a tiny prototype
project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;if you want more structure, where do you go? the npm libraries &lt;code&gt;tape&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;tap&lt;/code&gt; have ~20
dependencies each. &lt;code&gt;ava&lt;/code&gt; has ~40. i don&#39;t even want to think about &lt;code&gt;jest&lt;/code&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;i&#39;m sure these packages are great for certain things. but here&#39;s a minimal test runner i&#39;ve written:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/johanbrook/598d07fa89357f8577d6d0d6e88747a5&quot;&gt;Johan&#39;s Test Runner →&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;it works as you&#39;d expect:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;create a test file.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;import &lt;code&gt;test&lt;/code&gt; and write test cases.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;language-ts&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ts&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; test &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&#39;./_test-helper&#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; assert &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&#39;assert/strict&#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;test&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&#39;it works&#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
	assert&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;equal&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token boolean&quot;&gt;true&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token boolean&quot;&gt;true&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;i use node&#39;s &lt;code&gt;assert&lt;/code&gt; for assertions. want typescript support? add &lt;code&gt;esbuild&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;esbuild-register&lt;/code&gt;
as dev dependencies and run tests with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;language-bash&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot;&gt;node -r esbuild-register run-tests.ts
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the runner supports returning promises, as well as printing fancy file names for each test case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;i appreciate taking this approach before jumping to &lt;code&gt;npm install &amp;lt;dep&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;. it gives me very much peace
of mind, as long as you don&#39;t spend too much time maintaining your own tooling.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>March 15th, 2022 at 10:12:02 AM GMT+0</title>
    <link href="https://johan.im/mind#202203151012" />
    <updated>2022-03-15T10:12:02Z</updated>
    <id>https://johan.im/mind#202203151012</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;my latest favourite cocktail is this gin sour with bergamot and black tea. you&#39;ve probably felt the
scent of bergamot in earl grey tea or in perfumes. it&#39;s a highly aromatic citrus fruit: it looks
like a large, more spherical, lemon. it&#39;s also surprisingly hard to find here in stockholm – even
when it&#39;s in season.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;i found &lt;a href=&quot;https://feeders.se/2022/01/20/earl-greyish-bergamott/&quot;&gt;this recipe (in swedish...)&lt;/a&gt; and got
hold of a batch of bergamots through a restaurant friend. i&#39;ve translated the recipe to english
below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://johan.im/assets/posts/gin-tea-sour.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Gin tea sour&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ingredients&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;5 cl gin&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3 cl freshly squeezed juice from bergamot&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 cl earl grey simple syrup (see below)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 egg white&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Procedure&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pour gin, bergamot juice, simple syrup, and egg white in a shaker.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;shake like hell for a minute. it should create a lot of foam.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;add ice cubes to the shaker and shake until the shaker gets cold.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;strain into a coupe glass and decorate with something green or tea related.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the cocktail will get a lovely orange tea-like colour too!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Earl Grey simple syrup&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ingredients&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 dl water&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 dl cane sugar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 bergamot&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 strainers of black, neutral tea&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(this will make more syrup than you need for one drink.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Procedure&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;combine water and sugar in a pot.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;add the zest of the bergamot (the outer layer of the peel, save the fruit with its juice for the
drink). avoid the white layer beneath.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;put everything to a boil for a couple of minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;remove from the heat, add the tea strainers with black tea.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;let it sit for at least 5 minutes. it should gain a strong flavour.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;remove the strainers and let the syrup cool.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;strain (to remove the bergamot zest) and pour the syrup into a small bottle and store in the
fridge.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;i think the simple syrup is as best the first few days, but mine has lasted over a week now. just
don&#39;t forget it in there…&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>February 22nd, 2022 at 9:14:34 PM GMT+0</title>
    <link href="https://johan.im/mind#202202222114" />
    <updated>2022-02-22T21:14:34Z</updated>
    <id>https://johan.im/mind#202202222114</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;i want to get more tattoos but i don’t know what motifs yet. worst feeling.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>February 17th, 2022 at 12:48:07 PM GMT+0</title>
    <link href="https://johan.im/mind#202202171248" />
    <updated>2022-02-17T12:48:07Z</updated>
    <id>https://johan.im/mind#202202171248</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;The best fruits&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Banana.&lt;/strong&gt; they&#39;re full of vitamins, fibers, and natural sugars. they provide the best energy,
and are easy to a) carry around, b) peel. they&#39;re perfect.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mango.&lt;/strong&gt; whenever i get to pick flavours for (let&#39;s say) ice cream, i always pick mango (or a
combo of mango + something else). they &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; the best tropical fruits when it comes to flavour.
they&#39;re less easy to peel and deal with than a banana&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clementine/Satsuma/Tangerine.&lt;/strong&gt; easy to handle and somewhat easy to peel. the best of juices,
and full of vitamins. makes the day brigher.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pear.&lt;/strong&gt; sweeter than apples, with a soft, moist flesh full of fibres. they can be watery
though, so not as rich as mangoes and bananas.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&quot;1000&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pineapple.&lt;/strong&gt; i really hate these. ugly, hard shell, weird flavour. i would never carry these
on a trip, nor try to peel them as an ingredient.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>February 14th, 2022 at 10:20:37 AM GMT+0</title>
    <link href="https://johan.im/mind#202202141020" />
    <updated>2022-02-14T10:20:37Z</updated>
    <id>https://johan.im/mind#202202141020</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;i love this quote from Nils van der Poel (emphasis mine):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it&#39;s important to understand that you&#39;re not doing it for a gold medal. &lt;strong&gt;Regardless of
which life you chose to live, you will sacrifice something, that&#39;s the way it is.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As soon as you go in one direction, you also choose to not go in all other directions at the same
time. It&#39;s the basic precondition for going anywhere at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But on the path you take, you will experience fantastic things, even though it&#39;s uphill there will
be a great view when you&#39;re at the top, and that&#39;s what makes it worth it, to be on this journey
with people you love. It doesn&#39;t matter that much where the journey ends. A movie with a sad
ending is also a good movie - and a movie with a nice ending makes you happy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m very happy for this medal around my neck, and for getting all the way here. But why do you do
it? I don&#39;t think you get to pick your dreams, they pick us. It&#39;s up to us to realize them or not,
and it seems like people who try to realize their dreams are happier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nils van der Poel is a swedish olympic speed skater who just won two gold medals in the beijing 2022
olympics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;source:
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Radiosporten/status/1491090244652969984&quot;&gt;Radiosporten&#39;s Twitter (swedish)&lt;/a&gt;.
translated to english by &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=30329660&quot;&gt;jacobr&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
