<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>What's on Johan's mind</title>
  <link href="https://johan.im/mind.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://johan.im/mind"/>
  <id>https://johan.im/mind</id>
  
  <updated>2022-01-30T17:15:43Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Johan Brook</name>
    <email>webmaster@johan.im</email>
  </author>
  
  <entry>
    <title>January 30th, 2022 at 5:15:43 PM GMT+0</title>
    <link href="https://johan.im/mind#202201301715" />
    <updated>2022-01-30T17:15:43Z</updated>
    <id>https://johan.im/mind#202201301715</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;i&#39;ve bought a new &lt;a href=&quot;https://de.braun-clocks.com/collections/analogue-clocks/products/bc22-braun-classic-analogue-alarm-clock-white&quot;&gt;bedside alarm clock from Braun&lt;/a&gt;, and it&#39;s so pretty. when activating the back light, it glows in a cool amber light, and then fades away. drool. i have no idea about the timeline of things, but the green details feels very Apple-esque. i&#39;d guess Apple borrowed this from Braun when the former designed the iPods, which had similar green details around the physical knobs and switches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/0265/4388/2263/products/90fc68eb-f4b1-4b28-be66-3b9082e20428@2x.jpg?v=1631627468&quot; alt=&quot;BC22 Braun analogue clock&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>January 30th, 2022 at 2:02:21 PM GMT+0</title>
    <link href="https://johan.im/mind#202201301402" />
    <updated>2022-01-30T14:02:21Z</updated>
    <id>https://johan.im/mind#202201301402</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Kyla La Grange has &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/track/4vFF42BbvdSPksmBxOdMu1?si=LKNVDDREQOCc7NfJ_jb4Kw&quot;&gt;released new music&lt;/a&gt; and it’s really really good.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>January 24th, 2022 at 11:01:56 PM GMT+0</title>
    <link href="https://johan.im/mind#202201242301" />
    <updated>2022-01-24T23:01:56Z</updated>
    <id>https://johan.im/mind#202201242301</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;i&#39;ve bought a new domain for this site! from now on, it&#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://johan.im/&quot;&gt;johan.im&lt;/a&gt;. short and sweet. johanbrook.com redirects to johan.im.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;i appreciate these services/tools soooo much right now:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cloudflare&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fastmail&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cloudflare&#39;s dashboard is easy to understand and efficient enough to be dangerous — even though i&#39;m not a DNS/networking/cache elite ninja. Cloudflare might look simplistic compared to beasts like AWS, but if you look under the hood, they support more than what they show off (perhaps they should show off more?). example: like the noob i am, i just redirected &lt;code&gt;johanbrook.com/* → johan.im/*&lt;/code&gt;. but the paths after that slash of course weren&#39;t kept. so a URL &lt;code&gt;johanbrook.com/writings&lt;/code&gt; would just end up at &lt;code&gt;johan.im&lt;/code&gt; (the root). uh-oh. i read in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://support.cloudflare.com/hc/en-us/articles/218411427#h_6N5SySNYCjYUUnCKnC1Ea6&quot;&gt;help article&lt;/a&gt; that Cloudflare&#39;s Page Rules feature supports &lt;em&gt;wildcard referencing&lt;/em&gt;. tears of joy! so i could just do &lt;code&gt;johanbrook.com/* → johan.im/$1&lt;/code&gt; to keep those nice paths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fastmail&#39;s wizard for adding a new custom domain is so lovely. i could even pick Cloudflare as my DNS manager, and they&#39;d customise the wizard for Cloudflare&#39;s dashboard UI.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>January 23rd, 2022 at 11:50:58 AM GMT+0</title>
    <link href="https://johan.im/mind#202201231150" />
    <updated>2022-01-23T11:50:58Z</updated>
    <id>https://johan.im/mind#202201231150</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;the artist Meat Loaf died a few days ago. his album &amp;quot;Bat Out Of Hell&amp;quot; was the first album I recall playing on CD on my brand new music player when I was ~10 years old. that album – and especially the title track – was absolutely the thing that got me listening to classic rock as a kid, and then went on to widen my interest in music overall. i have such a strong memory of playing that album in my old room.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Bat Out Of Hell&amp;quot; was so &amp;quot;grand and majestic&amp;quot;, and the songs were sooo long. a stark contrast to the pop songs that was around in the 90s. and the guitar solos sure impressed me as a young child!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;bye, Meat Loaf 💖&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>January 17th, 2022 at 9:32:57 AM GMT+0</title>
    <link href="https://johan.im/mind#202201170932" />
    <updated>2022-01-17T09:32:57Z</updated>
    <id>https://johan.im/mind#202201170932</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.stephenwyattbush.com/2012/04/07/dad-and-the-ten-commandments-of-egoless-programming&quot;&gt;“Dad and the Ten Commandments of Egoless Programming”&lt;/a&gt; are all very nice.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>January 11th, 2022 at 10:16:07 PM GMT+0</title>
    <link href="https://johan.im/mind#202201112216" />
    <updated>2022-01-11T22:16:07Z</updated>
    <id>https://johan.im/mind#202201112216</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;hello world. this is me testing my new GUI for posting these small notes. i&#39;ll probably write a longer post about it later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;in a nutshell, i&#39;ve written a &lt;em&gt;barebones&lt;/em&gt; JS client to talk with GitHub&#39;s API to post a new file in this repo. no dependencies used. it was a fun challenge writing old school DOM JS manipulations again.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>January 6th, 2022 at 11:55:53 AM GMT+0</title>
    <link href="https://johan.im/mind#202201061155" />
    <updated>2022-01-06T11:55:53Z</updated>
    <id>https://johan.im/mind#202201061155</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;i&#39;m coding together something that will let me write post and notes in my static site from anywhere, and it&#39;s super fun. need to deal with github auth and their api, learning about Cloudflare Workers, and extending lume as i go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the idea is to create a new post or note file with a request from an authed github session. not sure how generic i want to make this code – it could be of use for others. the existing &amp;quot;CMSes&amp;quot; i&#39;ve seen for static pages are just &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt; much.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>January 4th, 2022 at 9:37:51 AM GMT+0</title>
    <link href="https://johan.im/mind#202201040937" />
    <updated>2022-01-04T09:37:51Z</updated>
    <id>https://johan.im/mind#202201040937</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;i&#39;ve rewrote my site (using &lt;a href=&quot;https://lumeland.github.io/&quot;&gt;lume&lt;/a&gt; 💛) and made a ton of tweaks. classic neverending parental leave chores. it&#39;s built with &lt;a href=&quot;https://deno.land/&quot;&gt;deno&lt;/a&gt;, which I love even more. i&#39;m finally free from the node/npm APIs and build systems! everything is much simpler now, and i should probably write about it in the even more classic post of &amp;quot;i&#39;ve rewritten my blog&amp;quot; which usually shows up in January every year.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>September 30th, 2021 at 12:00:00 AM GMT+0</title>
    <link href="https://johan.im/mind#202109300000" />
    <updated>2021-09-30T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://johan.im/mind#202109300000</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Summer is over, after vacation in August down on the Swedish west and south coasts. Weather was so-so, but it was nice with a change of scenery. We also spent the month of September in Florence, Italy, which was such a blast. We travelled abroad with our 10 months old daughter for the first time, and everything went quite well actually (I had expected the worst). I was so inspired by the stay in Italy, and hope I can bring some of that energy into the day-to-day life back in Sweden.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Monday I&#39;ll officially start my parental leave until April 2022. Scary but exciting. I&#39;m actually looking forward to just &lt;em&gt;not work&lt;/em&gt; for the first time in 7 years. Who knows what kind of person I&#39;ll be after this leave?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was inspired by the book &amp;quot;What I Talk About When I Talk About Running&amp;quot; by Haruki Murakami, so I want to start running this Autumn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, I&#39;d like to start making my own pasta. I took a pasta making course in Florence, and it was super fun. So simple! So fresh!&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>July 9th, 2021 at 12:00:00 AM GMT+0</title>
    <link href="https://johan.im/mind#202107090000" />
    <updated>2021-07-09T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://johan.im/mind#202107090000</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last day in the Swedish mountains, after a week of chilling and hiking. I wonder if I&#39;d like living here for longer periods of time, or if I&#39;d get cabin fever. I think I&#39;d adjust, but friends and family are far away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still learning programming in Rust. Still not 100% sure of what I&#39;m doing when it comes to memory management, but the &lt;a href=&quot;https://doc.rust-lang.org/book/&quot;&gt;official guide&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.possiblerust.com/&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Possible Rust&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt; have been of huge help. Rust feels like a very &amp;quot;intellectual&amp;quot; language (sooo much language theory has gone into it!), but I&#39;m struck every day of how friendly the documentation and 3rd party writings on the language are. I think a super good way of learning Rust would be to actually pair program with some existing Rust programmer you know, in a non-trivial project. So that you can ask about all the small things you run into, and can be unblocked and learn forever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m going to be on parental leave from October until ~April 2022. Am nervous, but looking forward. Will be a bit weird to be off work for 6 months since I started. But I have zero doubts in that I&#39;ll be able to chill in the new role of being a parent 100% of the time. I&#39;ll miss coding for work though, BUT I guess I&#39;ll need to find myself a sIdE PrOjEct like everybody else?!&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
