<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>What's on Johan's mind</title>
  <link href="https://johan.im/mind.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://johan.im/mind"/>
  <id>https://johan.im/mind</id>
  
  <updated>2023-04-11T23:43:47Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Johan Brook</name>
    <email>webmaster@johan.im</email>
  </author>
  
  <entry>
    <title>April 11th, 2023 at 11:43:47 PM GMT+0</title>
    <link href="https://johan.im/mind#202304112343" />
    <updated>2023-04-11T23:43:47Z</updated>
    <id>https://johan.im/mind#202304112343</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;lololll&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>April 11th, 2023 at 11:41:57 PM GMT+0</title>
    <link href="https://johan.im/mind#202304112341" />
    <updated>2023-04-11T23:41:57Z</updated>
    <id>https://johan.im/mind#202304112341</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;iOS!&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>April 11th, 2023 at 11:28:49 PM GMT+0</title>
    <link href="https://johan.im/mind#202304112328" />
    <updated>2023-04-11T23:28:49Z</updated>
    <id>https://johan.im/mind#202304112328</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;hej&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>April 11th, 2023 at 11:16:31 PM GMT+0</title>
    <link href="https://johan.im/mind#202304112316" />
    <updated>2023-04-11T23:16:31Z</updated>
    <id>https://johan.im/mind#202304112316</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;hej&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>April 11th, 2023 at 7:58:39 PM GMT+0</title>
    <link href="https://johan.im/mind#202304111958" />
    <updated>2023-04-11T19:58:39Z</updated>
    <id>https://johan.im/mind#202304111958</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The minimalism of &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/track/6rQWcomd5gHKdALTXcGw66&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Open House&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt; by Lou Reed and John Cale is superb. So eerie and perfect. Nobody can do Lou Reed&#39;s voice better than Lou Reed himself.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>March 20th, 2023 at 8:29:45 PM GMT+0</title>
    <link href="https://johan.im/mind#202303202029" />
    <updated>2023-03-20T20:29:45Z</updated>
    <id>https://johan.im/mind#202303202029</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;On the night to Friday, March 17th, I became a father for the second time. Insane! A little girl was born to us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to me now being deep into the kids thing, this time around didn&#39;t feel as scary as with our first. I am now able to embrace this moment to 150%, which feels a-mazing.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>February 19th, 2023 at 7:34:11 PM GMT+0</title>
    <link href="https://johan.im/mind#202302191934" />
    <updated>2023-02-19T19:34:11Z</updated>
    <id>https://johan.im/mind#202302191934</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Did a small re-align of my site. Nothing too big. Just some spring cleaning, visually. Feels good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve landed in a nice rhythm of doing exercise now. Combining running and weight lifting. My constant gripe with the latter is to have to eat so goddamned much all the time to get any growth effect out of the gym sessions, but whatever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watched &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;All Quiet On The Western Front&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt; yesterday. It&#39;s a Netflix produced film (but it was super good!) about a solider in the German army during World War I. It&#39;s based on the book with the famous title, a source of many dad phrasings over the years (dads throwing in the reference &amp;quot;all quiet on the Western front&amp;quot; in conversations when receiving the question &amp;quot;how do you do&amp;quot;). The film was amazing in the sense of production, but also (I guess) authenticity (the dialogue is German 💞). The sheer horror of war was pictured in a deeply touching and soul draining way.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>January 30th, 2023 at 8:53:22 PM GMT+0</title>
    <link href="https://johan.im/mind#202301302053" />
    <updated>2023-01-30T20:53:22Z</updated>
    <id>https://johan.im/mind#202301302053</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve finally stopped using Twitter now. Feels weird. The reason was that they shutdown API access for 3rd party clients, like the one I&#39;m using: Tweetbot. That was the last straw for me. I&#39;m out. I have zero energy for using Twitter&#39;s apps. I&#39;m going all in on Mastodon now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily, the creators of Tweetbot have released Ivory – an iOS app for Mastodon. It&#39;s the same look and feel as Tweetbot, which is amazing. I&#39;ve started to like Mastodon a lot now. I wrote &lt;a href=&quot;https://johan.im/writings/mastodon&quot;&gt;a post&lt;/a&gt; about it too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Long live Twitter. Goodbye, old friend 👋&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>October 27th, 2022 at 8:24:17 PM GMT+0</title>
    <link href="https://johan.im/mind#202210272024" />
    <updated>2022-10-27T20:24:17Z</updated>
    <id>https://johan.im/mind#202210272024</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;hi again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;last week, i was in portugal 🇵🇹 (right on the coast) with the rest of lookback. it was lovely to see everybody again. the heart is truly filled until next time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;we&#39;re going to south africa 🇿🇦 in november! we&#39;re gonna be in franschhoek and kalk bay, on the cape. really looking forward, since a) i&#39;ve never been in south africa, b) after researching, everything seem so cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;for the month long trip, i&#39;ve made a list of books to read:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Spy Who Came In From The Cold&lt;/em&gt;, by John le Carré&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Grand Union&lt;/em&gt;, by Zadie Smith&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vargarna Från Evighetens Skog&lt;/em&gt;, by Karl Ove Knausgård&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;At the Existentialist Café: Freedom, Being, and Apricot Cocktails&lt;/em&gt;, by Sarah Bakewell&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;What We Owe the Future&lt;/em&gt;, by William MacAskill.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;just the action of making this list makes me excited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;red hot chili peppers&#39; latest album &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/album/0KJc9ksnoJJsdpQxV3z5i1?si=n5gq6c42Tpm54YKkAY9DlA&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;return to the dream canteen&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt; is so good. i love anthony&#39;s smooth vocals, and john&#39;s solid guitar. they&#39;re so very musical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;i&#39;ve bought an watch even though i&#39;ve said i wouldn&#39;t. to my defense, it was a) a used one, and b) i&#39;ll only use it for exercising. it&#39;s really nice to not bring the phone when running, since i wanna track how good i do. however, i&#39;m really impressed by the watch so far. it&#39;s really a marvel of engineering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;i watch &amp;quot;house of the dragon&amp;quot; on HBO, and &amp;quot;rings of power&amp;quot; on amazon prime. the former is really good: even though it doesn&#39;t have the intricate storylines from &amp;quot;game of thrones&amp;quot;, i like the acting and focus on relationships between parents and children. i also appreciate the focus on the hardships for women of giving birth. &amp;quot;rings of power&amp;quot; is so-so. it feels too CGI, i think, and too &amp;quot;joyful&amp;quot;. it doesn&#39;t have the raw feeling of peter jackson&#39;s trilogy.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>August 28th, 2022 at 7:15:48 PM GMT+0</title>
    <link href="https://johan.im/mind#202208281915" />
    <updated>2022-08-28T19:15:48Z</updated>
    <id>https://johan.im/mind#202208281915</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;i bought myself a &lt;a href=&quot;https://global.hario.com/pickup03.html&quot;&gt;Hario Filter-in Bottle&lt;/a&gt; for making cold brew tea from a recommendation from a friend. excited for my new life as health guru.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
