<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/" xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>What Johan Is Reading</title>
    <link>https://johan.im/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://johan.im/reading.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <description></description>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Apr 2024 08:14:21 GMT</lastBuildDate>
    <language>en</language>
    <item>
      <title>Min Kamp 6</title>
      <link>https://johan.im/reading/min-kamp-6/</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://johan.im/reading/min-kamp-6/</guid>
      <description>Finished reading</description>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[I've finished the final installment of Knausgård's _Min Kamp_ (_My Struggle_) autobiographical series. The full
        collection of volumes goes over 3000 pages, so it suffices to say I'm pretty dazed now. Feels like I've been into
        a tumble dryer and out again.<!--more-->
        
        _Min Kamp_ is an epic amount of work. It retells Knausgård's childhood, adolescence, university years, and
        eventually becoming a father — this is over four decades of memories he accounts of in excruciating detail. This
        pioneering style of writing, and of course the fact that he writes about real people without changing too many
        names, was what made these novels unique.
        
        I feel I can't accurately describe how I feel about the series, since English not being my mothertongue. I can only
        praise the level of _detail and honesty_ that has gone into the pages. I am no writer, but I appreciate honesty in
        texts. Also have been a boy, teenager, a young adult, and now a father myself, I identify with areas and scenes
        brought up over the six volumes, each describing encompassing chunks of Knausgård's life.
        
        What's problematic, of course, with _Min Kamp_ is that he writes about people being close to him, and since he's
        being honest, it's not always positive things. His father, mother, brother, his then-wife, old girlfriends, old
        colleagues are described in the way Knausgård sees them. It's _his_ voice, _his_ views. But he had to do it,
        according to himself, in order to stay honest to the project.
        
        What I'm most touched and deeply affected by in the end, is his and his then-wife Linda Boström Knausgård's story. It begins in the late 90s, and describes their relationship from being lovers in Stockholm to being a family with
        three kids on the countryside of Skåne in south Sweden. He writes how Linda suffers from being bipolar,
        which climaxes at the end of the sixth volume. It's almost like they became fictional figures for me, since I
        wanted it to work out for them _so much_ I forgot they're real people (they separated in 2016. _Sob_). Their years
        together are described with such intimacy, which I think is required in order to make it honest and real. It made
        me so empathetic towards both of them. The whole situation: Knausgårds need to write, Linda's mental condition,
        their kids, their everyday life. I find myself being happy for them in the light moments, and sad in the dark
        periods. They become real, because they _are_ real.
        
        Knausgård shows that every person's life is indeed "interesting" and is a well of experiences from which you can draw stories from. Even though he admits later that he wouldn't have done the project if he knew the
        costs, I'm personally happy that he did, since it's a remarkable piece of work. Does he fully portray his wife
        Linda's authentic inner self? No. Is it right to write about his dead father and grandmother in the way he does?
        Maybe, maybe not.
        
        I've read quite many opinions about the series, and it's what you'd expect: much praise, but a lot of analysis
        going on about ethics, chauvinism, and self-centerism (is that a word?). In the end, I was entertained and adore
        Karl Ove Knausgård's style and angle.
        ]]>
      </content:encoded>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Apr 2024 08:14:12 GMT</pubDate>
      <atom:updated>2024-04-01T00:00:00.000Z</atom:updated>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Min Kamp 5</title>
      <link>https://johan.im/reading/min-kamp-5/</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://johan.im/reading/min-kamp-5/</guid>
      <description>Finished reading</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[See _[Min Kamp 6](/reading/min-kamp-6)_.]]></content:encoded>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Apr 2024 08:14:12 GMT</pubDate>
      <atom:updated>2024-02-28T00:00:00.000Z</atom:updated>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Min Kamp 4</title>
      <link>https://johan.im/reading/min-kamp-4/</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://johan.im/reading/min-kamp-4/</guid>
      <description>Finished reading</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[See _[Min Kamp 6](/reading/min-kamp-6)_.]]></content:encoded>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Apr 2024 08:14:12 GMT</pubDate>
      <atom:updated>2024-02-20T00:00:00.000Z</atom:updated>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Min Kamp 3</title>
      <link>https://johan.im/reading/min-kamp-3/</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://johan.im/reading/min-kamp-3/</guid>
      <description>Finished reading</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[See _[Min Kamp 6](/reading/min-kamp-6)_.]]></content:encoded>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Apr 2024 08:14:12 GMT</pubDate>
      <atom:updated>2024-02-13T00:00:00.000Z</atom:updated>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Min Kamp 2</title>
      <link>https://johan.im/reading/min-kamp-2/</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://johan.im/reading/min-kamp-2/</guid>
      <description>Finished reading</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[See _[Min Kamp 6](/reading/min-kamp-6)_.]]></content:encoded>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Apr 2024 08:14:12 GMT</pubDate>
      <atom:updated>2024-02-03T00:00:00.000Z</atom:updated>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Min Kamp 1</title>
      <link>https://johan.im/reading/min-kamp-1/</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://johan.im/reading/min-kamp-1/</guid>
      <description>Finished reading</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[See _[Min Kamp 6](/reading/min-kamp-6)_.]]></content:encoded>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Apr 2024 08:14:12 GMT</pubDate>
      <atom:updated>2024-01-24T00:00:00.000Z</atom:updated>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Det Tredje Riket</title>
      <link>https://johan.im/reading/det-tredje-riket/</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://johan.im/reading/det-tredje-riket/</guid>
      <description>Finished reading</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[I loved it just as much as the first one in the series (I loved the second one less). It's something in Knausgård's language which is so, so good.]]></content:encoded>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Apr 2024 08:14:12 GMT</pubDate>
      <atom:updated>2024-01-14T00:00:00.000Z</atom:updated>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tunnel 29 — The True Story of an Extraordinary Escape Beneath the Berlin Wall</title>
      <link>https://johan.im/reading/tunnel-29/</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://johan.im/reading/tunnel-29/</guid>
      <description>Finished reading</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[This is kind of a "dramatised" documentary of actual events. Tons of historical metadata along the way. It's a bit cheesy sometimes, but I totally admit it was a page turner. And most importantly, it taught me a lot about the real life behind the Wall, in East Berlin (hint: Stasi were the biggest assholes ever).]]></content:encoded>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Apr 2024 08:14:12 GMT</pubDate>
      <atom:updated>2024-01-04T00:00:00.000Z</atom:updated>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Berlin</title>
      <link>https://johan.im/reading/berlin/</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://johan.im/reading/berlin/</guid>
      <description>Finished reading</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[Continuing my journey towards being a fully fledged dad. 150% detailed account of the Allied invasion of Germany in 1945. So much stuff I didn't know. Lots of stories about the conditions of the soldiers, civilians, and the fates of prisoners (hint: all quite horrible).]]></content:encoded>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Apr 2024 08:14:12 GMT</pubDate>
      <atom:updated>2023-10-15T00:00:00.000Z</atom:updated>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Secret Pilgrim</title>
      <link>https://johan.im/reading/secret-pilgrim/</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://johan.im/reading/secret-pilgrim/</guid>
      <description>Book dropped</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[No notes]]></content:encoded>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Apr 2024 08:14:12 GMT</pubDate>
      <atom:updated>2023-10-01T00:00:00.000Z</atom:updated>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>